A Finding Aid to the Grace Borgenicht Gallery Records, circa 1953-1996, in the Archives of American Art AAA.gracborg
Archives of American Art
Grace Borgenicht Gallery Records
circa 1953-1996
AAA.gracborg
Archives of American Art
18 Linear feet
The records of New York City Grace Borgenicht Gallery date from circa 1953 to 1996 and measure 18 linear feet. The records include administrative files, correpsondence, financial and legal records, exhibition files, printed material, two scrapbooks, and photographic negatives of artwork. The majority of the collection consists of artists' files.
Grace Borgenicht Gallery.
Scope and Contents note
The records of New York City Grace Borgenicht Gallery date from circa 1953 to 1996 and measure 18 linear feet. The records include administrative files, correpsondence, financial and legal records, exhibition files, printed material, two scrapbooks, and photographic negatives of artwork. The majority of the collection consists of artists' files.
Administrative files focus on advertising, events, gallery renovation, artists' insurance, and writings about the gallery. Correspondence concerns galleries, artists, works of art, and gallery prints and includes correspondence with the Library of Congress, Hokin Gallery, and Raab Gallery in Berlin. Exhibition files are found for exhibitions of Milton Avery, Paul Burlin, Stuart Davis, and Wolf Kahn, and several artists from Germany, Japan, Korea, Mexico, and Canada, as well as for international art fairs. Artists' files mainly contain correspondence with galleries and patrons regarding the artists and their work, and with artists. Files are found for Milton Avery, Charles Biederman, Ilya Bolotowsky, Martin Chirino, Stuart Davis, Jose De Rivera, Roy Gussow, Philip Grausman, and Wolf Kahn, among many others. Financial and legal records include sales and operations ledgers, artists' contracts, and documents concerning arts organizations. Printed materials consist of exhibition announcements and catalogs. Two scrapbooks include clippings and other printed materials. Also found are photographic negatives of artwork.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 8 series.
Series 1: Administrative Records, 1970-1995 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1950s-1995 (2 linear feet; Boxes 1-3)
Series 3: Exhibition Files, circa 1970-1996 (1.3 linear feet; Boxes 3-4)
Series 4: Artists Files, circa 1950s-1995 (11.2 linear feet; Boxes 4-13, 16-22)
Series 5: Financial and Legal Records, 1953-1995 (1.4 linear feet; Boxes 13-15)
Series 6: Printed Material, circa 1950s-1995 (0.8 linear feet; Box 15)
Series 7: Scrapbooks, circa 1950s-circa 1980s (0.3 linear feet; Box 23)
Series 8: Photographic Materials, circa 1950s-circa 1980s (0.8 linear feet; Boxes 24-25)
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated in 1996 by owner Grace Borgenicht Brandt.
Biographical/Historical note
In May 1951 Grace Borgenicht Brandt (1915-2001) opened the Grace Borgenicht Gallery on 57th Street in New York City with an exhibition of Jimmy Ernst. At that time, the gallery was one of a handful that represented contemporary American artists. Jimmy Ernst, Milton Avery, Ilya Bolotowsky, Edward Corbett, Jose de Rivera, Roy Gussow, Wolf Kahn, and Gabor Peterdi were among the artists represented by the gallery.
The gallery held multiple exhibitions for individual artists such as Milton Avery, Wolf Kahn, Paul Burlin, and Stuart Davis. Although Borgenicht's main focus was American contemporary artists, the gallery also held several exhibitions featuring artists from Canada, Germany, Japan, Korea, and Mexico.
The Grace Borgenicht Gallery closed in 1995.
Related Archival Materials note
Also found at the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Grace Borgenicht Brandt conducted by Dorothy Seckler on January 10, 1963.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Separated Materials note
Also found in the Archives are papers loaned by Grace Borgenicht Brandt in 1963 for microfilming on Reel D112, including 72 letters from artists Leonard Baskin, Edward Corbett, Sidney Gordin, Wolf Kahn and Elbert Weinberg, to gallery director Grace Borgenicht (Grace Borgenicht Brandt), regarding their work, work in progress, travels, exhibition plans and other activities. Also included are Brandt's resume and a photograph of her.
Avery, Milton, 1885-1965; Biederman, Charles Joseph, 1906-2004; Bolotowsky, Ilya, 1907-1981; Brandt, Grace Borgenicht, 1915-2001; Burlin, Paul, 1886-1969; Chirino, Martín, 1925-; Davis, Stuart, 1892-1964; De Rivera, José Ruiz, 1904-1985; Grausman, Philip, 1935-; Gussow, Roy, 1918-2011; Hokin Gallery.; Kahn, Wolf, 1927-; Library of Congress.; Raab Gallery. (London, England); Art galleries, Commercial--New York (State)--New York; Gallery directors--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Scrapbooks
- Administrative Records, 1970-1995; Series 1; 0.2 Linear feet Box 3
  Scope and Contents note
  Files concern advertising, private events, gallery renovation plans, artists' insurance, and writings about the gallery.
  - Advertising, 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Advertising Proofs, circa 1985-circa 1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Artists Insurance Letters, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Events, circa 1985-circa 1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Renovation Documents, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Writings and Notes About the Grace Borgenicht Gallery, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, circa 1950s-1995; Series 2; 2 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Arrangement note
  General correspondence is arranged chronologically.
  Correspondence includes general chronological correspondence, letters with the Hokin Gallery and Raab Gallery, and correspondence regarding gallery prints for the Library of Congress. Artists and works of art are typically discussed in general correspondence.
  - Gallery Prints, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, 1950s-1969 (Box 1, Folder 8-11)
  - General Correspondence, 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 12-20)
  - General Correspondence, 1980-1986 (Box 1, Folder 21-23)
  - General Correspondence, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - General Correspondence, 1990-1995 (Box 2, Folder 4-15)
  - Hokin Gallery, 1975-1979 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Museums, 1953-1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Prints for Library of Congress, 1956-1966 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Raab Gallery, Berlin, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Exhibition Files, circa 1970-1996; Series 3; 1.3 Linear feet Boxes 3-4
  There are exhibition files for Milton Avery ("Avery in Mexico," "Milton Avery and His Friends," "Milton Avery: Impressions of Mexico"), Paul Burlin ("Paul Burlin: Late Paintings"), Stuart Davis ("Stuart Davis: The Formative Years 1910-1930"), and Wolf Kahn's exhibition at the Arts Club of Chicago. Additional files cover exhibitions of from Germany ("Die Bruke: Major Painitngs and Works on Paper," "Selected German Prints," "German Prints 1900-1984: A Selected Survey"), Japan ("Techno-Metaphysics"), Korea ("Six Artists from Korea"), Mexico ("10 Artistas de Mexico"), and Canada ("Fifty Years of Canadian Landscape Painting: A Selection"). The gallery's participation in the ARCO (Feria Iinternacional de Arte Contemporaneo) art fair, the Art Dealers Association of America's "The Art Show," and the Messe Basel International Art Fair are also documented. Other significant exhibitions include "The Gloucester Years," "Pastel Anthonology II," and "Still Life Anthology."
  - "10 Artistas de Mexico" (1993), 1992-1995 (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
  - ARCO (Feria Internacional de Arte Contemporaneo) Art Fair (1992), circa 1992-1992 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - ARCO (Feria Internacional de Arte Contemporaneo) Art Fair (1993), 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
  - ARCO (Feria Internacional de Arte Contemporaneo) Art Fair, Organizing Committee, circa 1992 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "Art 1994 Chicago: The New Pier Show" (1994), 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Art Dealers Association of America, "The Art Show" (1990, 1992) (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Art Dealers Association of America, "The Art Show" (1993-1996), 1992-1996 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "Avery in Mexico" (1981-1982), 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Chirino Traveling Show (1990-1991), 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "Die Brucke: Major Paintings and Works on Paper", "Selected German Prints" (1992), 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "Fifty Years of Canadian Landscape Painting: A Selection" (1987) (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - "German Prints 1900-1984: A Selected Survey" (1984), circa 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "The Gloucester Years" (1982), circa 1981- circa 1982 (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
  - "The Gloucester Years" (1982), Reviews (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Invitational Exhibition" (1983), circa 1983 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "Landscape Anthology" (1988), circa 1988 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Messe Basel International Art Fair, "Art 25 '94" (1994), 1993 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - "Milton Avery and His Friends" (1978), circa 1978 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - "Milton Avery: Impressions of Mexico" (1984), circa 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "Pastel Anthology II" (1987), circa 1987 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "Paul Burlin: Late Paintings" (1981), circa 1970, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - "Sculpture for Architecture" (1974) (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - "Six Artists from Korea" (1995), 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - "Still Life Anthology" (1990), circa 1990 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - "Stuart Davis: The Formative Years 1910-1930" (1983) (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - "Techno-Metaphysics" (1989), 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 13-14)
  - Wolf Kahn, Arts Club of Chicago (1981), 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Artists Files, circa 1950s-1995; Series 4; 11.2 Linear feet Boxes 4-13, 16-22
  The files are arranged alphabetically by artist surname.
  Artists' files consist mainly of correspondence with galleries and patrons regarding the artists and their work, and with many artists. The files on Milton Avery include documents for the Milton Avery Trust and writings about Avery. Jose de Rivera's files include preliminary writings by Dore Ashton for the book Jose de Rivera Constructions. Other artists' files are found for Max Beckmann, Charles Biederman, Martin Chirino, Jimmy Ernst, Janet Fish, Philip Grausman, Roy Gussow, Hans Hokanson, Angelo Ippolito, Rueben Kadish, David Lund, Gabor Peterdi, David Saunders, Sandy Walker, and Elbert Weinberg.
  - Artists Curriculum Vitaes, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Avery, Milton, General, 1950s-1985 (Box 4, Folder 17-24)
  - Avery, Milton, General, 1986-1995 (Box 5, Folder 1-16)
  - Avery, Milton, Correspondence Regarding Publications, circa 1980-1990 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Avery, Milton, Milton Avery Trust, circa 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 2-5)
  - Avery, Milton, Writings About Avery, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Beckmann, Max, 1980s-1995 (Box 6, Folder 7-12)
  - Biederman, Charles, 1970s-1988 (Box 6, Folder 13-16)
  - Biederman, Charles, 1989-1995 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Biederman Port Authority Commission, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Bolotowsky, Ilya, Publicity Documents, 1960s-1980s (Box 7, Folder 4-5)
  - Bolotowsky, Ilya, Trois Anges Ltd. Graphics Contract, 1969-1971 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Brown, David Lee, 1969-1995 (Box 7, Folder 7-9)
  - Burlin, Paul, 1962-1995 (Box 7, Folder 10-11)
  - Bush, Jack, 1987-1995 (Box 7, Folder 12-13)
  - Canadian Artists, 1987-1995 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Chirino, Martin, 1960-1980s (Box 7, Folder 15-19)
  - Chirino, Martin, 1980s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
  - Corbett, Edward, 1950s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 4-6)
  - Cuevas, Jose Luis, 1969-1982 (Box 8, Folder 7-9)
  - Currie, Steve, 1988-1995 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - D'Arcangelo, Allan, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Davis, Stuart, 1978-1990 (Box 8, Folder 12-15)
  - Derain, Andre, 1987-1995 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - De Rivera, Jose, General, 1950s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 17-18)
  - De Rivera, Jose, General, 1970s-1990s (Box 9, Folder 1-7)
  - De Rivera, Jose, Bibliography Cards, circa 1980s (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - De Rivera, Jose, Documents on Book Constructions, 1970s-1980s (Box 9, Folder 9-10)
  - De Rivera, Jose, Library of Congress Copyright Office, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - De Rivera, Jose, Writings by Others, circa 1980 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - De Rivera, Jose, Writings by Dore Ashton, circa 1980 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Ernst, Jimmy, 1969-1988 (Box 9, Folder 14-15)
  - Fetting, Rainer, 1994-1995 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Fish, Janet, 1993-1995 (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
  - Gill, John, 1986-1995 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Grausman, Philip, 1965-1980 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Grillo, John, 1975-1980 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Gussow, Roy, 1975-1991 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Hokanson, Hans, 1976-1990 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Howes, Royce, 1987-1995 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Hull, John, 1985-1995 (Box 10, Folder 9-10)
  - Ippolito, Angelo, 1972-1991 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Kahn, Wolf, 1956-1980s (Box 10, Folder 12-18)
  - Kahn, Wolf, 1980s-1995 (Box 11, Folder 1-6)
  - Kadish, Reuben, 1979-1995 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Kirchner, Ernst Ludwig, 1982-1991 (Box 11, Folder 8-10)
  - Lee, Jenny, 1993-1994 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Lehmbruck, Wilhelm, circa 1990s (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Leonard, Ruth, 1989-1991 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Lund, David, 1959-1991 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Mason, Emily, 1988-1995 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Milne, David, 1989-1994 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Opper, John, 1966-1995 (Box 11, Folder 17-18)
  - Peterdi, Gabor, 1953-1995 (Box 12, Folder 1-4)
  - Pozzi, Lucio, 1992-1995 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Radford, Matthew, 1993-1995 (Box 12, Folder 6-7)
  - Romberger, James, 1988-1995 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Roos, Gabriele, 1976-1981 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Rosen, Jane, 1988-1995 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Salemme, Attilio, 1977-1984 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Santomaso, Giuseppe, 1982-1984 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Saunders, David, 1983-1995 (Box 12, Folder 13-15)
  - Smith, Houghton Cranford, 1988-1995 (Box 12, Folder 16-18)
  - Thomas, Gwenn, 1988-1992 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Toepp, Wayne, 1988-1992 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Walker, Sandy, 1977-1983 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Weinberg, Elbert, 1960s-1995 (Box 13, Folder 4-9)
  - Welz, Rebecca, 1989-1995 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - White, Rodney, 1989-1991 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Bolotowsky, Ilya, Publicity Albums, 1963-1976 (Box 16)
  - Brown, David Lee, Publicity Album, 1970-1978 (Box 16)
  - Burlin, Paul, Publicity Album, 1962-1981 (Box 18)
  - Corbett, Edward, Publicity Album, 1959-1973 (Box 18)
  - Cuevas, Jose Luis, Publicity Album, 1976-1978 (Box 18)
  - De Rivera, Jose, Publicity Albums, 1946-1975 (Box 19)
  - Grausman, Philip, Publicity Album, 1974-1978 (Box 19)
  - Gussow, Roy, Publicity Album, 1963-1978 (Box 20)
  - Hokanson, Hans, Publicity Album, circa 1968-1980 (Box 20)
  - Ippolito, Angelo, Publicity Album, circa 1968-1980 (Box 20)
  - Kadish, Reuben, Publicity Album, circa 1971-1978 (Box 20)
  - Kahn, Wolf, Publicity Albums, 1954-1979 (Box 17)
  - Lund, David, Publicity Album, 1954-1983 (Box 17)
  - Opper, John, Publicity Album, 1966-1978 (Box 22)
  - Peterdi, Gabor, Publicity Album, 1951-1977 (Box 22)
  - Saunders, David, Publicity Album, 1979-1983 (Box 22)
  - Walker, Sandy, Publicity Album, 1977-1979 (Box 22)
  - Weinberg, Elbert, Publicity Albums, circa 1966-1982 (Box 21)
- Financial and Legal Records, 1953-1995; Series 5; 1.4 Linear feet Boxes 13-15
  The bulk of the series consists of sales and operations ledgers. Also included are files for artists contracts, documents regarding the Instituto de Artes Graficas de Caxaca/Francisco Toledo Non-Profit, and the London Arts Group.
  - Artists Contracts, circa 1955-1978 (Box 13, Folder 12-13)
  - Instituto de Artes Graficas de Caxaca/Francisco Toledo Non-Profit, 1990 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Ledgers, Accounts Payable and Receivable, 1975-1985 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Ledgers, General, 1985-1986 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Ledgers, Operations, 1976-1985 (Box 14, Folder 3-6)
  - Ledgers, Sales by Month, 1979-1985 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Ledgers, Sales by Name, A-C, circa 1953-1985 (Box 14, Folder 8-10)
  - Ledgers, Sales by Name, D-F, circa 1953-1985 (Box 14, Folder 11-12)
  - Ledgers, Sales by Name, G-I, circa 1953-1985 (Box 14, Folder 13-14)
  - Ledgers, Sales by Name, J-L, circa 1953-1985 (Box 14, Folder 15-16)
  - Ledgers, Sales by Name, M-O, circa 1953-1985 (Box 14, Folder 17-18)
  - Ledgers, Sales by Name, P-S, circa 1953-1985 (Box 14, Folder 19-20)
  - Ledgers, Sales by Name, P-S, circa 1953-1985 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Ledgers, Sales by Name, T-Z, circa 1953-1985 (Box 15, Folder 2-3)
  - London Arts Group, 1973-1974 (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Printed Materials, circa 1950s-1995; Series 6; 0.8 Linear feet Box 15
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  Printed materials consist of exhibition catalogs and exhibition announcements.
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1950s-1990s (Box 15, Folder 5-8)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1960s-1995 (Box 15, Folder 9-15)
- Scrapbooks, circa 1950s-circa 1980s; Series 7; 0.3 Linear feet Box 23
  Two scrapbooks contain clippings, certificates, photographs, and other printed material.
  - Scrapbooks, circa 1950s-circa 1980s (Box 23)
- Photographic Materials, circa 1950s-circa 1980s; Series 7; 0.8 Linear feet Boxes 24-25
  Photographic negatives of artwork are found here. A majority are labeled with the artist's name.
  - Negatives of Artwork, circa 1950s-circa 1980s (Box 24-25)